hello everyone
welcome to actin flab guest stream
number 18.1
we're here with
julian keverstein and michael kirchoff
as well as dave dean and steven from
actin flab
and we're really appreciative for the
authors for joining today to be
discussing some of their work we're
going to have
a presentation by the authors
and then following the presentation
we'll have ample time for discussion so
please feel free to write any questions
down in the live chat and we'll get to
it so without further ado
um julian and michael thanks a lot for
joining and
please take it away
thanks so much for inviting us we've
been we've been looking forward to this
particular session and thanks for
staying up late in the us and whoever
you are in europe for getting up early
it's only 3 30 in the afternoon here for
us so that's
more manageable in australia
i'll just share my screen
let's see and share
is that right yeah you guys can see that
bring that up
so that should all be clear in a second
is that right looks good
great um so the paper is called the
literalist fallacy and the free energy
principle
um it's a it's a philosophical
paper on the topic of scientific realism
scientific antiviralism instrumentalism
in the context of the fep or the free
energy principle
um i suppose just as a primer
this is a revised and resubmit stage
for our paper at this particular moment
in time
so any comments that we might be able to
get to further improve the quality of
the paper will of course be
welcomed
so let's let's start there will be a
little bit of i suppose conceptual stage
setting at the start just given the
nature of this particular paper and also
because it sort of speaks to a few other
issues that go beyond just a sort of
narrow focus on the free energy
principle
so this is the debate as it as it sits
or at least as we try to sketch it in
the paper
between scientific realism and
instrumentalism so let's just say
briefly what scientific realism is and
briefly what instrumentalism is and then
i'll we'll say a little bit more about
how to think about scientific realism
overall the point of the paper was to
sort of try to marshal a set of
arguments for why
at least a version of scientific realism
can be accommodated
by fep models
and it was motivated in part because it
seems like in the last few years there's
been a
there's been a flurry of papers
sort of in one way or another arguing
for scientific anti-realism with respect
to the fep or how to interpret parts
of that particular model so that's the
kind of that's the kind of setting we're
in
so scientific realism that's the view
that one reasonable goal for currently
best scientific theories
scientific models is to offer literally
true or probably true or approximately
true or probably approximately true
descriptions and explanations of target
systems i have here in bracket for
example natural phenomena
but it could also be artificial systems
in the context of artificial
intelligence artificial life for example
now by contrast then
instrumentalism or scientific
anti-realism
that's the view that scientific theories
and models are nothing but instruments
for prediction of observable behavior of
target systems
so here the the claim is something like
this um from an instrumentalist
perspective theory slash models they
have explanatory power
and that gets them some utility
but they're not in any in any sense of
the word truth producing so that one is
not to think about instrumentalists or
the instrumentalist position as uh
putting forth statements
about how the world is on the basis of
their models by which you can say
something say true or false about how
the world is
so the main question now is
for this particular paper we are
considering
is the fep truth producing in a way
that's consistent with scientific
realism
now one of course as i mentioned just a
minute or so ago we think it is indeed
consistent with a particular way of
conceiving of scientific realism
maybe a footnote here that's important
both scientific realism and
instrumentalism are quite
a multiple there's multiple different
versions of each particular uh framework
and that was it science so we're trying
to offer a reasonable general
characterization of these particular
frameworks in order to sort of get some
traction on the debate
so as i said there's a reasonable goal
of our best scientific theories and
models to offer these true or probably
true approximately two descriptions of
target systems
now here we we we draw inspiration from
peter guthrie smith
uh his book here erian reality that
tells us how perhaps to interpret that
particular general claim
he says the following he says it's a
mistake to express the scientific
realist position in a way that depends
on the accuracy of our current
scientific theories
so if we express scientific realism by
asserting the real existence of entities
recognized by science at this particular
point in time
then if those particular theories turn
out to be false well then the whole
framework of scientific realism turn out
to be false so we shouldn't think that's
what you have to do in order to advocate
for a kind of scientific
realism about scientific models theories
and their relation to target systems
so building on this we can say
so again this notion here is that an
actual unreasonable aim of science is to
give us these accurate descriptions well
that's not the claim that scientific
theories must be true now
and make truth producing claims about
target systems now i mean it's a nice
thing if they do but it is not a
necessary condition for
for one to adopt scientific realism
about scientific theories models
there's no commitment to the success of
the individual sciences so there can
there can be trouble in biology but we
can still hold for instance uh
scientific realism about for instance
the fep applied to the cognitive
sciences for example
now importantly and this is and this is
why i'm just spending a little bit of
time initially on scientific realism
the kind of version of scientific
realism we're interested in
is going to allow for theories and
models to posit
idealization for instance understood as
distortions
approximations
understood here is perhaps
inexactness of scientific models
they can propose fictional
entities for instance
entities that are not actual
and thus like in the here and now but
the important point is that
you can keep that view and still endorse
scientific realism because
one aspect here is that the long
term aim
of working with your scientific models
is for them to become truth-producing or
to become
more and more aligned with
the target systems that we're interested
in
and we'll finesse this viewer sort of
move along
now this issue between the scientific
realist and the instrumentalist as we
are considering it in the context of the
fep that comes up
when we consider what we
call
the map problem and this is not a term
of art that we have invented the other
authors in the both in the fep and
elsewhere that make use of this for
instance mel andrews in her nice paper
from 2021 in biology and philosophy that
speaks of this particular problem
so this is just a quote from the paper
that gets thinking about what our focus
is
so we're going to ask what is the
relationship between scientific models
constructing using the fep
and the realities these models purport
to represent
our focus is especially on the fep and
what if anything it tells us about the
system that is used to model and that
this is what we call the map problem
how does the map your theories your
models relate to the territory real
world target systems of which those
theories and models are maps
now if there's anybody joining on the
live stream um this is just a very brief
statement about what the free energy
principle says
julian and i and as well as ian are
working under the assumption that that
doesn't need to take long to introduce
that in this particular context
but very briefly then the ftp states
that a self-organizing system that tends
towards maintaining a non-equilibrium
steady state with its environment must
minimize free energy
where minimizing free energy at least
under a certain invasion interpretation
is to maximize model evidence
that is maximize the likelihood of some
data even a model of the system's
interactions with its environment
now how does the map problem arise in
the context of the fep
well it might arise if you're a say
a researcher working in artificial
intelligence and the aim is to build
robots that engage in active inference
for example
navigating or making decisions etc
so here the question becomes what's the
relationship between our fep model
understood as an active inference model
and then how
one engineers if you like
artificial agents to perform in
accordance with those particular models
what those models specifies in terms of
say
decision making belief updating and
selecting action policies for adaptive
behavior
a different way the map problem might
arise would be from the computational
neuroscientific perspective where one
might be interested in tracking
transitions across belief perhaps in
deep
generative models
and the map problem then is well how
does that
theoretical specification of free energy
minimization under active inference
how does that map onto what the brain
actually does in order to say shift from
beliefs to beliefs or to make decisions
about what to do in the world so that's
just a few examples of where this
particular issue becomes
prevalent
now
just to
situate this discussion a little bit
because there's a few tweaks and turns
in the paper and it's a large and
somewhat complex conceptual landscape
we're working in or at least it seems to
me
um we're just gonna try to situate this
a little bit more so you get a feel for
this
um
we got a nice reviewer comment uh that
sort of
introduces the issue here
so the comment is something like
if we take the free energy principle
like
many other theories across different
sciences then we can think about that as
a kind of model based approach to
science
and if you look at the little image over
here which is a modification of ears
uh sort of a little description of how
this works modified by graffiti smith in
the 2009 paper
we can initially start to develop a
description of a model
and to say something about what the
model system in question is
and the comment is something like this
we can study models for their own sake
as andrews has pointed out male as i
referred to earlier
any model that can be treated
realistically can also be treated
instrumentally scientists can disagree
about which bits of the model are meant
to be real
now this is important
in understanding how the map problem
arises so andrew's in the 2021 paper
gives us a whole list of different ways
one can see
the kind of mathematical structure
of the fep
being
interpreted as a scientific model
the work of michael weisberg is
influential
in the context of philosophy of science
philosophy of biology
so
she and he they can with sort of a
minimally three different models that
we're interested in the fab essay sort
of target less model the ftp is a
generalized model and then the fep is a
target directed model
now you can work purely on the
mathematics if you like of the free
energy principle
for the sake of just understanding the
model for getting your model description
right of your model system as per that
image
now here the point is that
that in and of itself
doesn't give rise to anything like the
map problem because you can disagree you
can come at that that work from an
instrumentalist perspective you can come
at it from a scientific realist
perspective but doing that kind of work
doesn't really allow you to adjudicate
between the two positions or so it seems
to us
so that would be the instance of a
target-less
model you're not asking questions that
relate from the model to a target system
you can treat the fpp as a generalized
model you can perhaps think of it as you
could model
theories natural selection
from the point of view of the fep but we
are not saying anything about the
evolvement of any particular kind of
species
that maps on to for instance a different
discussion as well which we consider but
we won't talk to unless it comes up in
the q a
about the role of the markov blanket
notation
now as we put it in the paper that gives
you a kind of generalized approach for
delineating boundaries but it doesn't
give you a approach for delineating
boundaries for any particular individual
in that sense it's a generalist take on
fep models on the basis of the markov
magnetic formulation
now the map problem first gets
interesting when you pursue a target
directed model
when you try to implement the
mathematical structures positive by the
fep in terms of a process theory such as
active inference
so you're sort of moving from a
mathematically general characterization
of the adaptive behavior to specifying
what a particular individual or a set of
individuals must do in order to engage
adaptively in the world so you start
committing yourself to an act to to
getting the sort of the right-hand side
of this this model uh or this little
image if you like uh saying something
about in which way do your model now
resemble the systems that you're
actually
aiming to explain or understand
something about
okay
so we should so once we have that we
should give the argument for the
instrumentalists
and then once we've done that we'll see
the kind of problem that we raise for
the instrumentalists that we think is a
kind of
a fallacy of inference
from certain considerations to certain
claims about the feb
so premise one here is that active
inference models on the under the fep
introduce distortions in representing
biological and cognitive systems
via idealizations
so one way to think about that might be
the introduction of variation of free
energy as a kind of distortion into the
framework in order to explain you know
it's kind of solve a computational
problem about how surprising it's
minimized
as well as in exactness via approximate
and one example might be something like
introducing this idea that
free energy minimization can be
construed mathematically as
akin to a kind of bayesian inference
would be an inexactness introduced into
the formalism
primarily because
well so it seems nobody thinks that the
brain quite literally
encodes something like basis theorem
okay premise two then is that scientific
realism requires that models provide
descriptions with target systems that
are literally true
so that's a
somewhat of a denial if you like uh if
you were the whole scientific realism
with respect to premise one
premise three then is that active
inference models are not true and
accurate representations of biological
and cognitive systems precisely because
of the issues raised in premise one
therefore active inference models are
false
there are best useful fictions
and
just to give you the references of where
we are drawing work from in terms of
defining the term idealization and the
term approximation here we're using a
nice paper by mcmullen on galilean
idealizations to think about
idealization and we are using a
canonical paper by norton to define
approximation
these are somewhat contentious
primarily because there's
as one might expect there's all kinds of
other takes on it but you have to come
down on one one side i suppose
so once we have the instrumentalist
claim up and running this is the kind of
fallacy that we're arguing that a set of
set of papers
defending instrumentalism in the context
of the fep is making and we coined the
literalist fallacy and just the prime
use though
premise two here is the claim that
scientific realism requires that models
provide descriptions of target systems
that are literally true hence the claim
the literalist fallacy because we're
going to show that's
that's not a necessary condition upon
which the base one's
defense
of scientific realism
so what we say is the mistake the
literalist fallacy is the mistake of
accepting or affirming about the fep
from the fact that active influence
model cannot literally map onto
biological and cognitive systems
a slightly different formulation that we
have here is that in this context of the
fep some find apparent discrepancies
between the map and the territory a
compelling reason to defend
instrumentalism about the fep and we
take that to be problematic
given this particular kind of fallacy
we identify this particular fallacy by
those defending instrumentalism about
the fep and we call it the little
fallacy here's this the second variation
of it if you like this is the fallacy of
inferring the truth of instrumentalism
based on the claim that the properties
of fep models do not literally map onto
real world target systems so so one one
question that might be interesting to
discuss in the q a is whether or not it
is indeed the problem for a
instrumentalist to infer the truth of
their own position on the basis of the
claim that the properties of fep models
do not map literally map onto real world
target systems
so the pushback here on the second
formulation is something like this
instrumentalists are not asserting the
truth of their own position that would
be self-contradictory
now there's a set of conceptual issues
here but i just wanted to flag the issue
and perhaps come back to it in the q a
it would take us too long to get into it
and they did somewhat philosophically
conceptual
here's some here's some evidence that
you like uh a set of papers across some
different topics that
that
we arguing are all committing this this
kind of fallacy
is a 2020 paper by venice and polito
that state they said that it remains
quote it remains disputed
whether it's the fep statistical models
or scientific tools to describe
non-equilibrium steady-state systems
which we call the instrumentalist
reading or are literally implemented and
utilized by those systems the so-called
realist reading and what they're going
to conclude is that since fep models are
not true and accurate descriptions of
these target systems instrumentalism
turns out to be the only option so for
us that's a lit that's the literalist
fallacy because it assumes
that the realist decision is
that your theoretical models literally
have to be implemented in target systems
for that kind of framework and the
philosophy of science to be up and
running
we're in about adele 2021 presumably
updated 2022 at some point this year in
their target article in bbs
focused on the ontological status of the
markov blanket formulism in the fep
now they argue that much of the
literature on the fep implies that
organisms literally instantiate the
mathematical structure of markov
blankets
they argue that such a use of the
formulism conflates a model with its
target system
now if you think that in order to use
the markov blanket formalism
productively even from the scientific
realist point of view that the
mathematical formulation of that
particular formula has to be implemented
in the actual target system
then you're permitting the literalist
fallacy because even the scientific
realist is going to push back against
that
colombo and palacios in a 2021 article
in biology and philosophy target the
issue of herbal dicity in the fep namely
that one can realistically model
biological systems as having anagrotic
density now they deny that ergodicity
captures properties of biological
systems and therefore the fep is
biologically implausible now the line on
that is that's that's a kin or a species
of the literalist fallacy precisely
because it's going to assume that the
theorists actually think
that it's part and parcel of target
systems that they have an ergodic
density
our take on it is no that particular
approach
to modeling uh state transitions
uh under the fep is a precisely that
it's it's a kind of um
it's a problem it's a sort of a it's an
approximation
scientific convenience
in order to say something about how
systems occupy states over time but you
shouldn't conflate that particular uh
perspective with saying that's literally
the case of target systems
i'll skip the last quote here
just for time considerations we can come
back to if there's
there's any issues
okay let's turn to some examples and
some cases
of this literalist fallacy and how to
how to think about it than in terms of
scientific realism
so in the paper we consider a bunch of
these sort of cases or examples we
consider
the notion of variational free energy
we consider the markov blanket formulism
we consider the role of bayesian
inference in these sorts of formulations
and then finally we turn to consider the
topic of ergodicity
now for this particular uh presentation
if you like we're only going to focus on
the first variation of free energy and
then the latter epididy and perhaps we
can come back to the other cases in q a
okay
um
it strikes us there's two different ways
of
interpreting
the variational free energy notation
primed here under the consideration that
it seems as if organisms are minimizing
variational free energy in the long run
so the as if formulation here which
seems ever pervasive now in the
literature um is not i think a one-way
street there's a couple of options here
that we now want to try to unpack
especially because we're doing the
presentation and especially because
we've been prompted to do so i think by
by a set of revenue comments but let's
get into it this is the sort of first
option if you like
that's gonna that's gonna deliver
a set of reasons for thinking that
instrumentalism is the case for the fep
and we're gonna push back on those
particular reasons
so uh variational free energy is an
information theoretic construction used
to compute how organisms are able to
resist decay by positing a variation of
free energy in an aquaponic rival
now under the fep for an organism to
exist it must keep its states within
certain bounds
okay so that's the generic opener
so i'll give you some examples now of
the as if formulation uh sort of
prompted by this quote from fristen the
ftp is a mathematical formulation of how
adaptive systems is natural
to decay
ramps that and colleagues 2020 paper say
this means that internal and active
states will look as if
they're trying to minimize the same
quantity namely the surprise law of
states it constitutes the thing a
particle or some preacher
so here we have the as if statement
they appear to perform this this kind of
minimization of variation of free energy
similarly in a 2019 paper um
any system that avoids surprising
exchanges with the world will look as if
it's predicting tracking and minimizing
a quantity called variational free
energy on average and over time now i've
included this because we're going to
speak to this one this particular paper
as a second option for how to think of
the acid formulation and how perhaps the
square acid formulations with a kind of
scientific realism
then as 2020 the system does not
actually predict infer track or minimize
the quantity called variational free
energy but it merely looks as if the
probabilistic model merely tracks
certain real statistical relations in
the organism environment system
so this particular reading here this
first reading the as if formulation of
variation of free energy leads to
scientific realism about active
inference models under the fep
and it does so essentially because we
have to sort of treat systems only as if
but not actually minimizing this
particular quantity
yeah
just jump in on this a minute so the
ramstead quotes there are saying that uh
what it looks as if the
system is minimizing is surprisal
whereas van s
shifts to talking about variational free
energy
so um
yeah
i think we could accept that it looks as
if the system is minimizing surprisal
because variational free energy is this
bound on surprisal yes so the ramstead
quotes are actually consistent with
realism
yes that they could be read as allowing
that
the system really does minimize
variational free energy and it looks as
if
in doing so it's minimizing surprisal
so perhaps we can come back to that in
the discussion
yeah i don't think that ramsteid and
colleagues are
necessarily best read as endorsing
instrumentalism
um
i think
it's quite consistent with realism
actually
yeah no i agree and i i think we'll see
that come out i sort of
recently explicit when we turn to the
second option to just step in if i don't
if i don't actually manage to pull that
out uh explicitly
very good yeah
so
basically what we can now assume is that
variational free energy under this first
half reading is a
mathematical fiction at least that's
what we're told these sorts of
constructs are used for fictions uh but
they do not actually exist
so how to kind of think about that then
because we we tend to agree with that
particular point
so
you can think that variational free
energy a bit like a galilean
frictionless plane for example
is a concrete entity
as in it has some mathematical
concreteness about it
but it's not one that actually exists in
target systems here the mass is not the
territory
so even though we can
we can we can kind of think of friction
as planes as being concrete in one sort
of sense of its mathematical
concreteness
one wouldn't want to infer that that
julian is a frictional plane for example
that that would be that would be false
and it would ultimately end up in in a
bad set of inferences
now here again we draw on the work of
guthrie smith in order to think sort of
more generally about the use of
fictional entities in the context of
science more generally but here's what
he says generally speaking he doesn't
dress anything to do with the fep
just to make that clear
now fictions do not exist he says but at
least many of them might have existed
and if they had they would have been
concrete physical things located in
space and time and engaging in causal
relations
so it's kind of counterfactual test
you can run on fictional entities and
science from the point of view given
here
now you can say fictional entities such
as variation or free energy
that might lack actual existence and
target systems
can be useful for understanding target
systems nevertheless
so you might say that active inference
models provide insight into the workings
of biological systems for instance with
helping to understand what a system has
to do in order to maintain homeostasis
you can also say something like the
following meaning that
under a kind of basian interpretation of
how one minimizes this particular
quantity you can draw some similarities
to how that
to how um surprisal is minimized in
actual target systems by understanding
something about the minimization of
variational free energy but there's a
kind of similarity relation one can draw
between depositing or fictional entities
in
the theoretical models and then what
actual target systems are doing
now
just to give you a sense of this so
motivated by active inference models on
the dfep par and colleagues say the
following about the significance of
their work on active inference i'll just
give you the quote and you can kind of
see this this is coming in
to to to being so in brief
we use magno in circular graphic graphy
in combination with eye tracking to
assess the neural correlates a form of
short term memory doing a dot uh
cancellation task using dynamic
remodeling to quantify changes in
effective connect connectivity
we found evidence that the coupling
between the dorsal and ventral attention
networks changed during the psychotic
interrogation of a simple visual scene
now they say here and i've highlighted
this intuitively this is consistent with
the idea that these neuronal connections
may encode beliefs about what i would
see if i were to look there and that
this mapping is optimized new data are
obtained with each fixation
so the idea here is that fictional
entities such as variational free energy
allows for the further understanding of
target systems by making precise how
target systems may minimize free energy
whether or not that be variational free
energy or
expected free energy
in the sense of minimizing their
surprisal and not directly in the sense
of minimizing these two notations
so the summary here that we give in the
article is that
the fep comprises what is known as
indirect representation of a target
system so it says something indirectly
about the operations of target systems
even if it involves the use of abstract
entities
it's an idealized approach representing
complex or unknown processes in the
world
it's standard practice to view
scientific models as indirect
representations of the real world target
system now furthermore most theoretical
models are composed of a set of mixed
claims now this is going this is rather
important for us to sort of preserve a
notion of scientific realism about the
fdp
basically and we use the work of spiel
out here
this means that the model will pass it
if through the presence of what he calls
both okay entities such as electrons and
their ilk and supposedly non-okay
entities such as numbers or theoretical
ideals
now we think the fvp is something like
such a model it's a model posed or
composed of mixed claims
it put forward all kinds of okay
entities neurons reflex acts etc and
perhaps what you might think of as
non-ok entities such as the variational
free energy notation where non-okay
entities has to be understood in terms
of not being literally true of their
target systems
so this gets us to the second
formulation that julian alludes to
alluded to earlier of the asif
formulation
now take us an example here from
dennett's 1996 book kinds of minds and i
think thanks to an anonymous reviewer
here for pointing us to this this idea
then it's so-called screeches
now these creatures are said to be able
to select from possible action policies
although it's not put exactly in those
in those terms in order to prune away
inferior options to avoid fatal
consequences so in this sense these
creatures have some kind of inner
environment where they can select
amongst possible actions
now here's the
tales of two densities paper that i
co-authored with
max ramster and cal fistin
um
i'm not going to
read you the quote here but the basic
idea is going to be something like this
that one can prune away unwanted action
policies
by testing what kind of expected sensory
observations
one might
encounter will want to elicit certain
kinds of actions
but whether or not one prunes away
action policies
the crucial part here is that that kind
of beliefs transitioning over possible
sensory outcomes given certain kinds of
actions can itself be characterized in a
fictional way
in in in a form of fictionalism as julia
mentioned earlier that is entirely
consistent as far as we can tell um
with scientific realism
so for the puberian active inference
feature one can think of trajectories
and suit over possible action policies
in terms of fictions as i just mentioned
and now we come back to our our
formulations of a fictional entities and
science from a previous from a couple of
slides ago
now you might say that action policies
are concrete belief states but they're
not actual they do not actually exist
they do not actually exist given their
counterfactual hypothetical
characteristics
yet whether to exist they would be
actual with some causal powers there
will be implications for inferring one
over the other
arguably some of the hypotheses come to
fruition and therefore exist
so what we have here is an sf
formulation of the of fep explanations
that
has a fictional characteristic to it so
part of the entities that compose our
fep explanations are fictional entities
but they're entirely consistent with
scientific realism about fep
explanations given the considerations
about the status of fictional entities
and science in general
okay so let's see we've been going for
about yeah 35 minutes i'll start
wrapping this up so we can get to the q
a second case one slide really quickly
about ergodicity just to just get us
thinking about this at least we can come
back to it
now fristen defines ergodicity in the
following way
one can interpret the average amount of
time a state is occupied as the
probability
of a system being in that state when
it's observed at random
okay now colombo and palacios in this
2021 paper in biology and philosophy
they say that phase spaces of biological
systems are structurally unstable
they're always changing and
unpredictable unpredictable making them
non-ergotic there isn't a set of fixed
states if you like that the system keeps
returning to if such a system is a
biological system on this particular
account by columbia and palacios
now they say that the fep trades off
realism for generality and mathematical
precision
and they do so in a sense to to to sort
of put pressure on this idea that the
feb can be thought of in terms that are
consistent with scientific realism
now it's true if you have you take a the
approach to the fep as a generalized
strategy to modeling
that the fep trades off realism for
generality and in the same time
maximizing mathematical precision
but i think here's here's the twist
so this would be the first way of
responding to this particular claim
if you turn the fep the mathematical
structure into a target directed system
what we get here we get to work with
specific systems so now you get to
increase the level of realism in your
in the relationship if you like between
your model and your target system
a second way of thinking about
ergodicity is that yeah okay it be true
that they don't map up they don't have
biological plausibility
but you can think of ergodicity as a
convenient modeling assumption
so the fap doesn't claim that biological
systems are literally ergodic there's
even the loosening in the literature now
to saying locally ergodic or there's
even a further loosening the shifting
talk of ergodicity uh
entirely to talk about kind of nest
densities and so on we where you can
actually still retain this kind of
metastability this this level of change
and this degree of unpredictability
so to conclude arguments for
instrumentalism about the fep at least
the ones that we are considering i'm
sure there's one or two we have not
considered trade on the literalist
fallacy they accept or affirm
instrumentalism on the grounds that the
properties of active inference models
under the fep do not literally map onto
biological systems
if we are correct then there is a
version of scientific realism that is a
live and tenable option with respect to
efep
thank you
awesome
okay
great times
um perhaps for the first word we'll go
to julian just
feel preach maybe say hi give your first
take and then we'll go to the acting
flab participants yeah so thanks for
having us it's going to be fun to talk
about this paper um i think we should
just jump straight into discussion
rather than me add anything onto what
michael already said
he gave an excellent summary of the
paper
so let's see what you guys make of it
okay so age or beauty
where do we begin
um
uh
dave or dean or stephen who would like
to go first all right stephen first and
then either dave or
well i'll just like say thanks for the
book that you published a few years ago
about the third wave it was actually the
key book that kind of
made me keep going with active inference
after i first heard about it because uh
so it was a really really cool supposed
to hear boundaries because i've been
looking at
inactive embodied approaches and
so just that's the first piece um
and um so in there you talk about the
idea of markov blankets you're not
directly but the idea of things being
dynamic and
changing
and um
i'm curious whether when you're thinking
about instrumentalism
there's a there's a
in some ways the
the danger of instrumentalism or is it
starts to everything gets referred back
to maths
and then the maths isn't tethered to
reality because it's instrumental
and you can't it can be kind of a
challenge then as we try where we're
trying to bring in the four e's
um to think about well how how does
this start to map onto
the way that organisms are trying to get
a grip on the world
in a bit more of a literal sense outside
of the model
and so um
yeah i'd be interested in your thoughts
about
this this question of um
the the ability for
um the modeling to
be used in something almost a way to
get into phenomenon that might be
happening during this minimization
process
michael do you want to start
i i i can start um
well one i think one thing that's
important there just stepping back and
thanks for the nice words on on the book
that's always a pleasure to hear
the instrumentalist i suppose is is just
sort of as i said making a truth
claim is off the table for an
instrumentalist partly because
the definition of instrumentalism is
the sort of not to put forward any kinds
of statements about the world that can
be true or false
now they can say that you have
observations
you know you take in observations about
how systems work and that's fine
one one line there that's been pushed a
bit in the literature now is to say well
you can then you can be agnostic about
whether those kinds of observations
can sort of truthfully reflect or you
know
oppositely falsely reflect anything
about the actual world
now my sense is that and and this is
just my sense that scientists
given different
tasks and activities questions and focus
points will shift a bit
between these and and that's in a sense
why i had this notion of why we have
this notion of of a targetless model
i think precisely because that's the
domain we we don't need to come down on
one or the other side clearly the model
for the sake of its for for gaining more
understanding
you know a nice example i was talking to
an ecologist on the weekend is just
thinking about these massive climate
change models
right with this hyper practical goal
but yet they're so wonderfully complex
that one spends one's career
figuring out how the model works and
that's and that's okay uh in a sense but
i then shifting it and trying to answer
uh your question
i think some of the work that julian and
i have been doing on the sort of ever or
on occasion this is soften that shifting
boundaries
delineated by appeal to markov blankets
tells us something concretely
about such systems
so we can start thinking a bit about the
differences between say the spider and
the spider web relative to with whether
or not the australian or private has
just eaten its web or whether it's
producing its web so in that sense you
might think
that you know it's it's 7th sensory
is shrinking and expanding depending on
you know what time of day it is
so yeah i might as and to add to that i
i i'd like to think that
but i'd like to think that it's the
ambition of
even theoretical neurobiologists
or
if you know from depending on the domain
or issue they're targeting
is to if you're working in the context
of psychiatry on the basis of fep models
do you want to understand something
about
well actual uh psychiatric disorders
that we as human beings may
may go through
and then and you want to understand the
the mechanisms of how that of how that
works so you can intervene in the right
kind of way now if you want to do that
presumably you have to say something
about how those mechanisms work
and so you can you can quite literally
as i said manipulate them if that's
possible in one when one way or another
anyway so that's my initial take on that
i want to go in a slightly different
direction on the how does
the free energy principle relate to
these ideas about
embodied inactive extended cognition
um
well
thomas
van s and uh innis hippolyto
both argue for
an instrumentalist reading of the free
energy principle in order to uh
to show how it could be consistent with
a non-representational understanding of
cognition
and so they are they're keen on avoiding
the idea that the brain literally
represents the world by
encoding a generative model
and the way that they avoid that
interpretation of the free energy
principle is by
endorsing the claim that the free energy
principle is just a useful fiction
for modeling the brain
um
and we think there's a couple of
different
issues that are getting mixed up here
so one is
representational readings of the free
energy principle and uh karl kristen
often says that uh
the brain
um doesn't have a model but is a model
that the organism as a whole
is a model of its environment
and here he's picking up on ideas from
cybernetics like the the good regulator
theorem
the law of requisite uh variety is it
from ashby
um
[Music]
so
that idea of the organism being a model
of its environment
um
we think can be read in a realist way
actually
but but also as suggesting a a
non-representationalism
uh so this came up a little bit when
uh michael was talking about pop aryan
creatures
where they're able to because of the
deep
uh hierarchical nature of the generative
model
and try out possibilities
before they act on them
and that's sometimes taken to imply in
the in the philosophical literature
that
the
organism if it's able to to
do that kind of counter factual
inference
it must have some kind of model of these
possible states of affairs
that it's carrying out inference over
and so that gets you back into a kind of
um representational reading of the free
energy principle again
but uh
we are offering uh
an interpretation of the free energy
principle where we take very seriously
this idea that the organism is a model
but doesn't have a model
and
and therefore that opens up the space
for a realist interpretation
of the free energy principle
um that is also non-representationalist
or inactive
and
and that's that i think the space that
thomas fan s for instance thinks is not
available to proponents of the free
energy principle
but rather than go into why we think
he's wrong let's let me just stop there
because i've said quite a lot already
thank you for the responses
so
dean
well i think i'll ask both gentlemen for
your opinion on this i i think if
if you set your argument up as
a literal one
you're gonna you're gonna find yourself
into trouble because
um
i
i think if this thing kind of gets
resolved there's no debate if it's
metaphorical
because you have to have a minimum of
two i mean with these markov blankets
you got internal and external
you need you need minimum of two just so
that you have discrimination just so
that you can tell
variation in the world and that's what
metaphors allow for so
i'm just wondering
why we're not arguing
for both that it's the synthesis of the
instrumentalist
and that way to measure and filter
what's in and what's out because we do
measure that
and and filter for that and also the
relational piece i still like to bump
into edges so i agree with you as an
organism i am the model until i fall off
the cliff right so
if we if we looked at this as a metaphor
instead of literally wouldn't that kind
of
at least smooth out some of the
differences instead of versus
its and this
equals that
in in a metaphorical sense what are your
thoughts in that i don't think you can
have both instrumentalism and realism
although
max ramstead has said things along those
lines that he wants to try to well then
i'm with max best of both worlds yeah
but uh but the difficulty is that these
positions actually come into conflict
contradict each other
because one says that the free energy
principle
does not
map onto anything in the world so we
can't
make any
claims based on the free energy
principle about
how cognitive biological systems are
organized
it's literally just a modeling tool
so it can help us to predict make
predictions about
the behavior that we can observe of
biological or cognitive systems but but
the free energy principle
doesn't correspond to doesn't map onto
anything in the behavior or the
organization of biological and cognitive
systems and that to me seems in conflict
with the idea that
the organism is
a generative model if you say the
organism is a generative model then
that seems to me to commit you to the
idea that
the free energy principle is describing
something about how
biological cognitive systems are
organized and therefore
it's uh it's so
it ought to be construed in realist
terms not in instrumentalist terms now
you said something else about metaphor
there
yeah science introduces all kinds of
metaphors
and i think that that introduces a kind
of
distinct set of issues really
from the instrumentalism and
versus realism debate because we can
still ask for how do we interpret those
metaphors
so no doubt it's true that science
engages in
metaphorical talk all the time
but it is once you get into the question
of how to interpret the metaphors that
then
the realism instrumentalism issue comes
back again
so can i just
do one quick follow-up if i focus on the
instrumentalism
or the realism and not focus on the link
with the with the two arrow ends the
metaphor i i i absolutely appreciate
what you're saying julian if if i
if i pick one camp with the other
then i'm not focused on the metaphor but
what if i'm just exclusively looking at
that link as opposed to the the opposing
camps
can i i i'm very comfortable i'm i'm a
contradiction i'm a human being
right so i'm not sure why i have to pick
a side
i'm you haven't convinced me about that
yet but
yeah
i mean
depends a bit about how you how you
flesh out the term metaphor here right
so if we went back to the uh
that little image i had from gear you
had you know your model description
model system and some target system
so they say for instance you pass
metaphorical entities i suppose is that
what you have in mind there by metaphor
i'm talking about i'm talking about the
process of the
of the way to be able to link to
discrete or discriminatory
ideas or
objects or because i want to be able to
hold up the relationship and the measure
of that relationship i don't want to say
that i have to discard one in order to
take up the other
maybe it's useful to bring in the markov
blanket here as a metaphor for the
boundary
so the blanket seems like a good
metaphor for capturing the boundary of a
of a particle or an organism
right
and
so then we can ask well what is the
relation between that markov blanket
concept where you can where the markov
blankets are nested
and so you can find them at multiple
scales of organization multiple temples
spatial scales
what's the relationship between that
nesting of markov blankets and the
self-organizing systems that we're
we're using them to model
and
so i think that's where you get to when
you try to unpack the metaphor
there's a nested markov blankets is a
metaphor
and how do we then interpret that
and for michael and i the way to
interpret that metaphor is to think of
self-organizing systems as literally
having this
well not literally that's
vacant use of words isn't it
as uh
to think that there is a nested
organization within uh self-organizing
systems
that can be modeled and described
indirectly using the mathematics of the
free energy principle or using the
the formalism of markov blankets so
using the bayes causalness
it's yes on that note you use these
particular constructs i think on the
basis of what julian just said to
actually guide your research
in the sense of figuring out something
about how your target systems are
organized so the one way of casting this
in this in the jargon we've been using
that you
you distort you introduce a distortion
that you think you need to take
literally for instance the mathematics
underlying this particular markov
language of formalism
but you use that in order to guide and
direct your search
now that's important because that's the
that's the kind of key to our particular
to the way of thinking for us about
scientific realism that we can have all
these distortions and all these points
of inexactness in our theoretical models
however the ambition is to say something
about the target system that's the
that's where the sort of conversation
between the instrumentalists at least a
version of that the version of the
scientific realist framework uh
come apart now there's i should say
there's there's there's a set of good
reasons for thinking that the two
positions and philosophy of science are
mutually exclusive they can't be true
at the same time
and one is the positive of a set of
metaphysical claims on behalf of the
scientific realist
it's typically the case that one is
committed to the following there's some
kind of mind independent reality
okay now that can't be the commitment of
the instrumentalist because you can't
possibly because you have no you're not
producing the truth about how the world
is
the second metaphysical commitment is
that we can somehow get a grip
on uh unobservable causes
of our observations
but that's not an option for the
instrumentalists they can say something
about their observations of your
empiricists for example you can't you
can't start making
influences from that
to unobservable causes of those
observations but metaphysically there's
there's something at stake
when you have a discussion that goes
that considers these expansive
sort of broader considerations and
positive science
but those are metaphysical commitments
and i suppose we can argue
so to make it more concrete again going
back to the nested markov blankets and
the reason that we
we describe self-organizing systems in
those terms is because of how the
the faster processes are enslaved by
slower processes so you see this
this circular causality
and
that's described in uh
in
complex systems theory and
so
there's there's a
there's a dynamics that you can observe
in
living self-organizing systems
that
um that can be in exactly and
approximately described using
the formalism of markov blankets
and and it's because of that similarity
or resemblance between the
the formal apparatus that we're using
when we employ
uh base nets and the
the
modeling
formalism of markov blankets
it's because there's that kind of
similarity or resemblance between the
models that we're making as scientists
and the
dynamics of self-organizing systems
that we think it makes sense to
interpret that metaphor
in realist terms
does that make sense
well yeah i
i
again i wouldn't argue that
that if you if you do place yourself in
one camp you
you reject
what maybe the other side is arguing
what i'm thinking of is the
the statistical probability as a
distribution allows for perforations
meaning
the metaphor al is i wouldn't say it's a
bridge but it's kind of an escape patch
to boundary cross
and i mean quite literally if i use a
metaphor
i i get out of the constraint of
of not having that other person share
the idea unless we can arrive at some
convergence around something that we
both understand
from the past in order to be able to
project into that
that new set of congruencies so
i don't want to take up all of this
conversation i just wanted to see i
think that the issue here is really
something to do with what philosophers
do
where we like to disagree and argue with
each other right
now
that works for some people depending on
their personality and for other people
it doesn't work so well they prefer to
try and find agreement or
to find a way of communicating with each
other for us and as philosophers i think
disagreeing and arguing is not to fail
to communicate is that
it's just what we do as philosophers and
what that made me think about is um very
few people are in the position of
putting their name and a year and a
version on an idea
and being like the um avatar of the idea
like godfrey smith 2009
longino 2013. here's what the idea is
and um
dean or anyone who might be interested
in applying these ideas might have less
of a qualm with shifting their regime of
attention
even within a sentence
from one usage to another
and it's um in the fine art and science
of philosophy
where some of these um
minds become fleshed out and we can
really see like
how deep
the
logic goes
and that's like kind of like
higher overtones
in the symphony of thought and then you
know dean's just fiddling away on the
subway trying to trying to get whatever
currency they get up there in canada um
let me go to dave with a question
um because you haven't gone yet and then
uh stephen afterwards
okay um
coming at this whole question
particularly the question of metaphor
my background is i'm coming at this from
general semantics through the
cybernetics theory of learning teaching
through george lakoff's grounded
metaphor theory and through mark saul's
conscious ego so when you say
metaphor dot dot dot i say well who's
actually driving
the analysis who is it that has to be
appealed to
and i would say look the the
interpretation is done by
the metaphoric structure
why is that a good grounding because the
fundamental grounding of the entire of
every living
control system
the speed of updating the
the question of how existentially
imperative
that you not violate your priors
down through very delicate questions of
of
mathematical formalisms it's all
grounded in
the decline of
avoidance or approach
and decline of pain versus pleasure so
it's all grounded it's got a basis your
entire
structure of
um
[Music]
of inference of induction your whole
induction is already ground and so don't
worry about what the metaphor means
in terms of
theories
ask what do the theories mean in terms
of metaphor
don't be shy about telling me i've gone
off the deep end
every last person i respect has been
accused of going off the deep end
i might i might i might like i might let
julian take first dips here so i can
sort of get myself into into my own
headspace all right um
so
i like what you how you describe
metaphors and uh and the place that they
have within the free energy principle
where they're grounded in these
perception action emotion processes and
so
for fep that
what
everything is organized around is
these imperatives to resist
disintegration
and
and so it makes sense to me that
the metaphors we use in in communicating
with each other and thinking
are
in the end gonna
inherit there and be grounded in
in
life processes
and
that's something that we talk about in
terms of the life-mind continuity
thesis coming out of inactive ideas in
philosophy
the philosophy of biology
uh so there's an interesting connection
there between uh
the embodied cognition ideas that lack
often johnson are using and
and the the four e ideas so i think
that's what you were just describing
but uh
but that comes up at this from a
slightly different direction to to what
we're concerned with in our paper
um
where
what we're looking at is say
a matlab model
that somebody might make of uh in
simulating active vision like thomas
paris done
or
micah allen when he's looking at how
to model the interactions between heart
rate
and fear perception
and he's constructing like a
a simulation and in silico model
using the mathematics of the free energy
principle
to describe those kinds of interactions
between intraceptive processes like
monitoring of your heart rate
and extraceptive perception say
of
fearful images of faces making fearful
expressions
so that's a kind of in silico model
that's been made there
and what can we learn from those sorts
of simulations about
say interactions between heart rate and
visual perception
and that's where our our sorts of
questions come up
because you can think while the
the in silico simulations that are being
made
they're just um
instruments for making predictions about
say heart rate how heart rate's going to
interact with perception
um
and the the simulation can be
useful for
um predicting the kinds of data that we
could measure
but
the simulation itself isn't
gonna
give us knowledge of
how
the intraceptive system
interacts with
visual perception
and and we just say no that's wrong the
simulation can actually tell you
something important give you a kind of
knowledge maybe in the long term so we
have to look
over time and look at all of the
refinements that are going to happen in
active inference models
before we can actually
arrive at something that is a true
accurate description
but in the meantime the kinds of
approximations idealizations that we're
operating with when we make these kinds
of in silico simulations
are still telling us something important
about how
uh how the mind is organized how
living systems are organized
okay so that's the sort of claim that
we're making can you see that that's
sort of a little bit a tangent from what
you were asking about metaphor
maybe it isn't you can explain why you
see how you see them coming together
i have probably uh stated my my point in
an overly political way i was very
excited i was really
i am very excited about what you're
doing um
kind of like when muhammad the
the the opponent finally lands a really
solid blow on muhammad ali and elise is
okay enough playing around let's
let's hit that uh no i'm very
sympathetic i invited professor solms to
this discussion i certainly hope he's
going to watch the film um
no i'm i'm i'm very much on your side
i'm just saying i think what the i think
the the the
embodied
perspective the um
the pre-galilean perspective where
valence where value where teleology
are
viewed as the foundation or at very
minimum a co-equal foundation of the
entire intellectual structure the entire
research structure i think that is
exactly correct
um and i'm really pleased for instance a
subtle
british nuance perhaps that professor
used the same uh professor christian
uses the term
teleology so often in such an
an important sense i think that already
by itself involves hitting back yeah
but he always says he's deflating
teleology doesn't he he loves this word
deflation
something that we can see in in physics
as well
[Music]
and uh
yeah michael found something very
interesting in a in a
a youtube video from pristin about uh
where he was responding to
some some presentations that he'd heard
where he described describes how
uh this variational free energy relates
to to gibbs free energy michael did you
want to come in on that yeah i mean this
is definitely well well beyond sort of
my my pay grade with social media
probably with some people in in our
group here and in our audience well
we'll be here
basically the basic gist of it is
something like this
that you can you can describe
transitionings across belief states by
appeal to variational free energy
and that's nice that gives you a nice
sort of computational modeling language
to to speak about state transitions
across different beliefs
so so the so the claim is here
and it claim is interesting because it
allows for an even tighter
grip between your fictional constructs
and actual systems that you can give a
formulation of those
state transitions
by mathematically showing an equivalence
relation across the variation of free
energy
and the gibbs free energy which then by
definition allows you to show in energy
spent per joule or something like that
but it what it actually costs
to change one's beliefs for example
uh in the context of the fep now that's
that's that's great if that's the case
because that brings you even closer from
your model from your model space to your
target system space
but that that's a bit like when somebody
asks me and okinawa well how does the
octopus
mechanistically select its action
policies well i'm not a marine biologist
and i'm not a specialist in octopi i
mean that that that's not for me as a
philosopher to tell you and i have i'm
gonna i'm gonna cheat out and provide
the same sort of reason for not going
any further than that
but it's a good example i think um
yeah the reason i brought up was because
you were talking about teleology and
and what
kristen does in deflating that notion is
actually bring it back to
to something in physics as well like
gibbs free energy and the free energy
principle shows you how you can take
something that looks like it's going
back to aristotle but actually show how
to bring it into contact with
um with
the mathematics that we now have for
understanding self-organizing dynamical
systems
i mean it's i think it's just an
important note there so even if
the term teleology is being used in the
literature one ought not to confuse it
with the sort of notion of a final cause
as per the aristotelian system right so
so we have we have sort of a final cause
and ultimate end point that one
necessarily strives towards
right but rather that self-organization
is somehow inherently purposeful and to
me that's what strikes me as right but
it also destruction is a deflated notion
of teleology
yeah but
there's there's lots more we could say
on this before it's for another session
isn't it
it's a little bit of a tangent from what
we're currently talking about true
cool um stephen and then i'll have a
question and then we can sort of
land
yeah i think this this question about
what we can model with the fbp or what
fep is able to be used to do modeling on
using variational free energy
and
what
the model is
and i think you've kind of resolved this
to some extent by distinguishing
modeling from models so there's
instrumental
models there's
realist models and there's this process
of modelling
and one of the things about non and i
think in some ways you don't say
non-linear i mean non-linear dynamical
systems might be better than that
but
the the thing with those systems is
and
is that they are
in this case anyway generative
and we've been looking at and i was
actually talking to daniels in our tools
session like about how these bayesian
graphs can be thought of and one of the
things
is that
generally of a modern you try and fit
things to your model like in psychology
you fit someone to the model of
psychology right that can be the problem
because now this person's being fit to
sit with all these models
well in this case these models generally
always generate
the data
and but they generate a little bit
different each time because it's
stochastic so you see that the way they
evolve and that's what we're sort of
getting at so
building the model can be a useful
design thinking tool to think about how
it would be structured and then you get
this idea of modelling
and and this is actually maybe timeless
with what dave was saying a little bit
because my belief is that at the moment
all the ways that we are able to model
are very low dimensional like extremely
low dimensional
however i do believe i've been looking
at stuff
where phenomenologically it would be
possible
to use experience as the raw instrument
so i think high dimensionality
can be done
through
there is a potential for high
dimensionality so there's this question
of like when we're modeling
using models which are low dimensional
to such an extent and they even like
often are partially observable
markov decision processes so they're not
even actually saying the data coming in
has been aching
necessarily through
you know you either have these
psychological
models which are very low dimensional
and are partially observable so it's
gone up and it's hit the point of
beliefs and then they start to look or
they have these incredibly
particulate models starting from like
the first atoms of life or whatever
and
i think that your intuition is probably
right actually in terms of there are
then
because i've we've been looking at some
of this in terms of phenomenologically
there is there ways that
experiential
information can be modeled in
or put into these models
um
and so it doesn't only have to be
these very low dimensional ones which
may be so low dimensional that maybe
that's part of the problem it's not that
the fep
is
real it's just what they're using to
model it is still so low dimensional
yeah that's a nice question um
let me at least attempt a form of
response um
so julian and i ian met the other day
and was just sort of chit chatting here
and since you did mention micro
precision processes
i suppose one way of conceiving of this
if you like low dimensional versus high
dimension or kind of simplicity versus
complexity but kind of inaccuracy versus
more accuracy distinction would be just
a sort of
quite often one finds that those sorts
of processes are modeled in discrete
states
and and my my assumption is that that's
a simplification because it makes work
somehow more tractable
right so it's manageable you can you can
write the code on the basis of of this
discrete state
transitions for example
um and and and still learn something
even if you you sort of think that maybe
state transitions are continuous for
example right
um
another thing that's more
meta i suppose to that new is just it's
sort of the following so we're quite
inspired by a philosopher by the name of
michael weisberg so his name is appears
frequently now in the paper
and he has this it's really this really
nice paper from
2006 i believe it is all seven in
biology and philosophy where he gives
you two different approaches to a model
based science
we follow one in part because we don't
think it's very feasible to do the other
one he refers to as a kind of brute
force approach now i suppose this is
going to give you all the high
dimensionality that you can imagine
that given computational power to pull
it off on that approach the goal is to
have the values of all the variables you
can identify in your target system
reflected
in your model
this is you have a super high degree if
you like the correspondence between your
model system and your target system
but
the catch is that that particular
ambition
is extremely difficult given the sheer
complexity of real world systems
so the alternative
is to say well then any other kind of
model based approach
in sciences if you can't achieve that
degree of completeness if you like is to
use idealizations
so by necessity almost you have to
simplify i suppose that would be one way
of thinking about why we why we have low
dimensional models and why one uses low
dimensional models can you use
experience to improve those models
um
yeah i i'm not sure perhaps it seems
like you ought to be able to
ask a slightly different question but i
see stephen wants to come back so i'll
hold my comment for a minute yeah cool
well just one that i think i suppose
the dimensionality is so low that it's
almost like even if you made it a
thousand times more it still
would be
it's still useful because it shows the
dynamics shifting
which is a little bit different to most
models
however
yeah there's like
it's
it's it's it's
i don't know how many zeros it has been
magnified by in terms of multiplying the
complexity but that that that that um
that might be anyway so that that i
think it's a good point you're making
though yeah
thanks well let's take the casper hes
deeply thought effect model i don't know
if you know that one
so there's a
there's a variable in that model a
matrix the g matrix
which is
uh
which is trying to capture the
minimization of expected free energy
and the role that that plays in
selecting between action policies
and then and the idea is that uh
that that g matrix is something that's
changing over time
um
such that you can do better or worse
than expected
at
minimizing expected free energy
so there's a there's a variable there
which i guess is still there
gonna yield models which are low
dimensional in your sense but
but it it's still
um being used to model something
um that
is i think phenomenological in the end
namely valence
and
so
now
the mole i would draw from that is that
something that's an idealization an
approximation
because it's low dimensional
doesn't necessarily mean that that that
modeling tool that you're using there
that's that has this low dimensionality
you can't still
um
be used to describe
something high level and
phenomenological namely valence
and and that goes back to what dave was
saying before i think that the valence
is actually something that's built into
free energy minimizing systems because
variational free energy
is
a way of describing a way of indirectly
representing
is something that's fundamental to life
and which is this
tendency to avoid decay or
disintegration
and
so the low dimensionality i think
doesn't uh doesn't stand in the way of
using this as uh to model very high
dimensional
phenomenologically deep thick
concepts like valence
yeah that's a really good example
actually just one point on that and it
also
we're talking about
general because i do agree with the idea
of if we're saying
what are generally tractable
dynamical processes which maybe is
another type of realism in a way or it's
realism but to think of that
is
it does show that affect becomes a
plausible way
which pretty well hasn't i don't know
any other way to think about it
previously it's why we start to get into
consciousness
as well with mark soames
is
yeah it gives this plausible way
where what was relegated in our
scientific world because basically
consciousness was taken away by
psychology
and feelings were kind of
these this lower down ideas like well
wait a sec this is actually
the all-encompassing way to
know what you think
so that's actually because i actually do
a lot of work with metaphors and one of
the things that happens with metaphors
is people what's the metaphor of knowing
when you get something right
like what's it like to know something so
if you ask a mathematician what the
answer is to a problem
they don't get an answer on a computer
screen they actually feel the answer
being right
so they've kind of somehow and then
what's that like and then you can
process that as a spatial metaphor in
the room
but the
that you said it's affective so yeah i
do
agree with what you're saying and i i
what i'm interested as well is working
backwards from an effective state
and trying to plot out people's
low dimensionality
another way but that's for another
conversation but i i i do agree with
what you're saying
but i don't know whether you would say
that
dynamics is different to realism
in
physical
physical ways
so in that model that the g vector is uh
it's being used to set precision on
action policy so
which action policies can you be
confident in that's a kind of
metacognitive process in that
it's not just
acting based on some gut feeling
you know in in the way that you
described but
but using that feedback from the body to
to
uh assign precision so to
to look at how reliable
a prediction error is in relation to
your predictions
when the quantity that you're minimizing
is this expected free energy quantity
um so there's something global going on
there i think which gets you closer to
what you
what you're looking for when you're
thinking about consciousness
and
something in the global dynamics when
you're thinking about the g
vector
so
i'll just read out one
question from the chat and the answer
could be as simple as read the paper or
give a thought
and then i'll ask a closing question for
the authors so the question is from
matthew mctigue
and they wrote
how do we resolve the controversy of the
conflation between heuristic and markov
blankets
what metaphysical legwork should be done
to defend an ontological markov blanket
okay so so the question is something
like we don't really take that
opportunity one sneaky movement they say
go go read the greenback idiot paper but
um
moving from heuristics to
ontology i think i think julian has
already touched on that quite a bit when
speaking on the sort of multi-scale
characteristics of self-organizing
systems
um such that you just you so if you have
as part of your model and this is our
preferred approach here
uh the formula isn't like the mark of
blanket formulism then of course you're
not going to be saying that heuristic
this would be the literalist fallacy
it's going to just be mappable onto
this multi-scale
structure that comprises the system so
now you have to interpret that's the
next step in this modeling move you have
to interpret these sorts of notations
under a certain description such that
you can start thinking about what it is
about biological
uh organization that reflects in that
indirect sense that we're working with
these sorts of heuristics so that's the
work that one should do
but it's not it's not the kind of thing
that we discuss at length in one section
of the paper we call the section the
paper moves across four different
domains that has to be done with some
swiftness and level of generality to
bring the philosophical point home
but
that would i mean i think that that's
that's a separate paper actually that
that little question so thank you
matthew for that
awesome
so just one closing um question
as you are reviewing and revising the
paper
who is your audience
and how would it impact the next
several months or years of active
inference and free energy principle
research and application if people were
to really
direct the regime of attention and
understand what you're talking about and
update their generative models
accordingly
william do you want me or usually go
first i'm happy to go first initially
with initial thoughts so
i wanted to to bring up
the
recent paper by
miguel aguilera and um
and
chris buckley and others um where
the
the problems that they raised there
about how to take the free energy
principle
and uh and use it to to model
uh
real
biological cognitive systems and they
take very simple system and then show
what kinds of assumptions
you need to build into the free energy
principle in order to
to
use it to model those systems
and they argue that those assumptions
are are unrealistic
and they pick out a very small class of
systems and those systems are unlikely
to be biological cognitive systems
so that looks like bad news for the free
energy principle
and
but not from the perspective of our
paper
because what our paper shows is that all
of those assumptions that they identify
are actually exactly the kinds of
idealizations and approximations that
that don't rule out
taking the free energy principle to
to
indirectly represent
biological cognitive systems
and so the contribution of our paper to
the community i think is to just
point out that
you know even if we
look at the assumptions that underlie
the free energy principle and think well
those don't literally apply to
biological and cognitive systems
that doesn't rule out the possibility of
still
making active inference models and
and using them to
to learn important things about
their biological cognitive systems it
would only rule that out if you think
that
those systems literally have to
instantiate the assumptions that
uh
that are built into the fep before you
can apply the fep
and but we've argued no those
assumptions don't need to literally
obtain
and they can just be idealizations and
approximations
so so the contribution i think from of
our paper to the community is to say
well
there are these real challenges but they
don't stand in the way of using the free
energy principle to carry on doing
active inference models and learn
something important from those models
okay now if we can achieve that that's
certainly a job well done
um i think in terms of the terms of the
audience
perhaps outside um
just the technical very specific niche
of the the free energy principle
but i mean one one would like to hope
that a bit like when you had steven uh
on a few weeks back talking about free
energy a user's guide
which we crafted as a sort of
the ambition in part was of course to
introduce these sorts of conversations
into the context of philosophy of
biology
and then hopefully they'll they will
they will see the light of day
i think similarly here and i'm sure
julian will agree that you know i think
these these sorts of papers that take up
like broad picture discussions and the
philosophy of science with say an
emphasis on the free energy principle
will bring
an audience from the philosophy of
science into contact with with the kind
of you know area speciality that we're
working on
i would like to see that as a as an aim
as well i think secondly as well
or secondly just that
just
working through with some precision
these kinds of conceptual details
in this highly mathematical and and
sometimes
really abstract domain that is the free
energy principle is important
uh
precisely also i think for the sciences
working on it to have a feel for what
what is the conceptual assumptions of
making some claim
right so so you're also like
conceptually sort of
engineering or
this this this debating in a particular
sense that can be fruitful i think for
non-philosophers working on a knife a
bit like what julian was touching on
awesome well
michael and julian thanks so much for
the paper and also ian for co-authoring
on the paper and best of luck with it
dave dean and steven and also matthew
thanks for participating this is a
really interesting discussion and we
hope to continue the conversation
however you all would like
thank you thank you
thanks guys
good night see you later everybody
you